Guide to the Max A. Lauffer Papers, 1915-2013 UA.90.F99
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Talks and Lectures, 1938-2013; II.
  - Religious and Non-Technical Talks, 1946-2000; 2.
    - "What are the Roles of Research and Publication, and How are Data Evaluated," Pitt AAUP, March 12, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - "The Cost of Survival: The Control of Nuclear Power", March 4, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - "Scientific Development and World Change", October 18, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - "Science and Your Child," Hillcrest PTA, May 18, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - "Christian Attitudes in the Nuclear Age", October 7, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - "Jesus of Nazareth: Scientist", October 21, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - "Career Conference in Science and Engineering", November 30, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - "The Threat of Nuclear War", January 30-31, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - "Atmospheric Testing", January 30-31, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - "The Social Responsability of a Scientist", March 3, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - "Science, Scientists, and Liberal Education", April 18, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - "Henry Frank in Pittsburgh", December 10, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - "World Conference on Church and Society," Geneva, Switzerland, July 12-26, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - "War and World Order", 1967 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - "Law and Order- with Justice", October 8, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - "The Church as I See It", March 21, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - "Relevance", April 2, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - "The Social Mission of the Church," Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, September 2, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - "Remarks," Alumni Dinner, Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, May 1, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Does the Church Have a Social Mission?", March 5, 1972, February 11, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "Western Pennsylvania's Contributions to the Age of Science," Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, May 4, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Christian Attitudes in the Nuclear Age", May 23, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Ground Zero Talk", April 1982 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Assorted Subjects, 1960-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Biophysics and Interrelationship Among the Sciences" (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - "Can We Control the Super Bomb?" (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "The Control of the Environment for the Health of Man: The Role of the Physical Sciences" (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Definition of a Scientist," "Biological Immortality" (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "The Future of the Natural Sciences at the University of Pittsburgh" (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "High School Physics as a Preparation for the Study of Science and Engineering" (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "Nuclear War and World Order" (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "On the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research" (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "Physics and Medicine" (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - "The Renaissance of American Idealism in Liberal Arts Education: A Scientist's View" (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "Science and Religion" (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "A Scientist Contemplates the Brotherhood of Man" (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Other Assorted Talks, 1959-2013; 3.
    This subseries contains copies of speeches given at professional lecture series and other speaking engagements. There is also material regarding the Tousimis-Lauffer Distinguished Lecture Series, which was established by a former student in Lauffer's honor, which continues after his death.
    - Twentieth Annual Priestly Lectures, Penn State, May 20-24, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Twentieth Annual Priestly Lectures, Penn State, Certificate, May 20-24, 1946 (Map-case 5-6, Oversize 1)
    - American Chemical Society- Pittsburgh Award, December 29, 1987 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 20)
    - Salk & Sabin Talks, July 19, 2000, November 29, 2001 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 21)
    - Tousimis-Lauffer Distinguished Lecture Series, Department of Biological Sciences, 2008-2013 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 22)
    - Phillips Lecture, Phi Lambda Upsilon (Map-case 5-6, Folder 23)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1959 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 24)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1960 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 25)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1961 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 26)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1962 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 27)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1963 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 28)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1964 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 29)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1965 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 30)
- Articles, 1934-2011; III.
  This series consists of articles written by Lauffer, most of which are scientific, though there are a few that are related to religious topics. This series also contains official reprints of articles separate from the journals in which they were originally printed. There are also a few book reviews written by Lauffer and several articles about Lauffer, as well as many fragile newspaper clippings.
  - Articles by Lauffer, 1934-2004; 1.
    This subseries contains articles that Lauffer has written on various scientific and religious topics. It is arranged chronologically by the date in which the article was published.
    - List of Publications, 1938-1985 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 31)
    - "Studies on the Absorption and Elimination of Nicotine Administered Orally for Chickens and Techniques Involved," Master of Science Thesis, Penn State, 1934 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 32)
    - "The Future of Natural Sciences at the University of Pittsburgh," PITT No. 37, Summer 1949 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 33)
    - "Physical Chemistry of Viruses," Record of Chemical Progress Vol. 10 No.4, Fall 1949 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 34)
    - "Blood Lipoproteins and Arteriosclerosis," PITT No. 42, Autumn/Winter 1950-1951 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 35)
    - "The Physical Sciences," Public Health Reports Vol. 69 No. 7, July 1954 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 36)
    - "The Control of the Environment for the Health of Man- The Role of the Physical Sciences," PITT No. 52, Summer 1954 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 37)
    - "The Detection of Infectious Agents in Biological Preparations," unpublished, 1955 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 38)
    - "Evaluation of Serum Lipoproteins and Cholesterol Measurements as Predictors of Clinical Complications of Atherosclerosis," Contributor, Circulation Vol. 14 No. 4, October 1956 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 39)
    - "A Skeptic's Faith," THINK Magazine Vol. 24 No. 10, October 1958 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 40)
    - "Skeptical Faith," Science of Mind Vol. 32 No. 8, August 1959 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 41)
    - "Correlation of Ionizing Radiation Effects with Physical Changes in Viruses," Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences: Inactivation of Viruses Vol. 83 Art. 4, January 13, 1960 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 42)
    - "...for Academic Research," The Science Teacher Vol. 32 No. 4, April 1965 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 43)
    - "Hydrogen Ion Uptake upon Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein Polymerization," Journal of Molecular Biology Vol. 116, 1977 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 44)
    - "Motion in Viscous Liquids," Journal of Chemical Education Vol. 58, March 1981 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 45)
    - "The Significance of Entropy-Driven Processes in Biological Systems," Comments on Molecular and Cellular Biology Vol. 2 No. 2, 1983 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 46)
    - "Calcium Ion Bonding by Isolated Tobacco Mosaic Virus Coat Protein," Journal of Molecular Biology Vol. 170, 1983 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 47)
    - "Contributions of early research on tobacco mosaic virus," Trends in Biochemical Sciences Vol. 9 No. 1, September 1984 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 48)
    - "Comparison of the Entropy-Driven Polymerization Reactions of E66 and Vulgare Tobacco Mosaic Virus Proteins," Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics Vol. 236 No. 1, 1985 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 49)
    - "Entropy-Driven Polymerization of Ribgrass Virus Protein," Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics Vol. 238 No. 1, 1985 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 50)
    - "Effects of Dipolar Ions on the Entropy-Driven Polymerization of Tobacco Mosaic Virus," Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics Vol. 242 No. 2, 1985 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 51)
    - "History of Virus Research Between 1930 and 1950", 1987 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 52)
    - "History of the Biophysical Society & Biophysics", 1990 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 53)
    - "Life Begins When?," SciTech Vol. 13 No. 1, February 2004 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 54)
    - "Electronic Birefringence of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Solutions," "Polymerization of TMVP," articles & notes (Map-case 5-6, Folder 55)
    - "Vitamin A in its Relation to Carotene: A Historical Review" (Map-case 5-6, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified Article (Map-case 5-6, Folder 57)
  - Reprints of Articles, 1937-1985; 2.
    This subseries consists of official reprints of some of Lauffer's articles. These reprints are printed in their own booklet and do not include any other part of the original publishing journal or magazine. They are arranged chronologically by publication date. Lauffer had given numbers to some of the reprints so those are arranged by number in ascending order, but within that numbering system the reprints had been arranged chronologically.
    - Article Reprints, 1938-1939 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 58)
    - Article Reprints, 1940 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 59)
    - Article Reprints, 1941-1942 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 60)
    - Article Reprints, 1943 (Map-case 5-6, Folder 61)
    - Article Reprints, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Article Reprints, 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Article Reprints, 1947-1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Article Reprints, 1950-1951 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Article Reprints, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Article Reprints, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Article Reprints, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Article Reprints, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Article Reprints, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Article Reprints, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Article Reprints, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Article Reprints, 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Article Reprints, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Article Reprints, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Article Reprints, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Article Reprints, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Article Reprints, 1975, 1977, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Article Reprints, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Article Reprints, 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Article Reprints, undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Article Reprints 36-54, 1945-1949 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Article Reprints 55-79, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Article Reprints 80-106, 1953-1959 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Article Reprints 107-120, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Article Reprints 121-138, 1961-1965 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Article Reprints 139-155, 1966-1969 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Article Reprints 156-168, 1970-1978 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Article Reprints 169-184, 1980-1985 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Reprints by Wendell M. Stanley, Lauffer's mentor at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1937-1939 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Reprints by Wendell M. Stanley, Lauffer's mentor at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1941-1958 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews by Lauffer, 1943-1945; 3.
    This subseries contains Lauffer's reviews of other books, which were published in various journals.
    - Plant Viruses and Virus Diseases by F.C. Bawden, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Annual Review of Biochemistry edited by James Murrary Luck, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Frontiers in Chemistry, Vol. 4 edited by R.E. Burke and Oliver Grummit, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Studies in Biophysics: The Critical Temperature of Serum by Lecomte Du Nuoy, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Articles about Lauffer, 1945-2011; 4.
    This subseries consists of articles about Lauffer written by other people. It primarily contains journal and magazine articles, but there are also several newspaper clippings.
    - Newspaper Articles, 1940s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Article (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - PITT No. 21, Spring/Summer 1945 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Alumni Review, Summer 1945 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - PITT No. 45, Winter 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - PITT No. 53, Winter 1954-1955 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - PITT Ten Year Report, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - The Triangle Vol. 15 No. 11, November 1957 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - A Report on Professional Activities, University of Pittsburgh, October 1, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - The Pitt News, December 10, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Presbyterian Life, January 15, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Southminster Presbyterian Vol 25 No. 1, February 1970 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - University Times, Arpil 17, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - The Patriot-News, Harrisburg, PA, November 11, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Biophysical Society Newsletter, July/August 2004 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Pitt Magazine, Fall 2006 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - World of Giving, Fall 2006 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Biophysical Society Newsletter, July 2011 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Presbyterian Congregation of Middletown Newsletter, September 2011 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Biographies for Publications, General, 1960-1988 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Biographies- "Who's Who" Series, 1979-1986 (Box 11, Folder 27)
- Books, 1943-2000; IV.
  This series consists of books and book chapters that Lauffer wrote or to which he contributed. There are several drafts of one particular chapter that he authored for A History of Biochemistry. This series also contains several booklets of various topics that Lauffer owned, as well as books that were inscribed to him by the authors, many of whom were his friends and colleagues.
  - Book Chapters by Lauffer, 1945-2000; 1.
    This subseries consists of Lauffer's work on chapters for various scientific books to which he was contributing. The bulk of the subseries is documentation of his work on a chapter for A History of Biochemistry, including several drafts, figures, and notes for the chapter.
    - Chapter 4- "Tobacco Mosaic Virus and Its Protein" (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - "Forward," Studies in Biophysics: The Critical Temperature of Serum by Lecomte de Nouy, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - "Entropy-Driven Polymerization of Proteins: Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein & Other Proteins of Biological Importance," from Physical Aspects of Protein Interactions, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Ch. 4 in A History of Biochemistry, Comprehensive Biochemistry Vol.41, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Galley proofs (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," early drafts, June 26 & October 11, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," draft (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Draft 3 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Draft 4 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Draft 5 (Box 11, Folder 37-38)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," Draft 6 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," final draft (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," extra figures (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," figures slides (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - "Half a century with TMV and biophysics," dictation on microcassette (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Books by and Contributed to by Lauffer, 1938-2000; 2.
    This subseries contains Lauffer's work on several books that he either wrote or to which he contributed, including a book entitled Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics that he was writing with Howard Schachman and was never published. This subseries also contains Volumes 1-30 of the Advances in Virus Research series, of which Lauffer was a long time editor.
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.1, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.2, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.3, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.4, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.5, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.6, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.7, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.8, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.9, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.10, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.11, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.12, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.13, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.14, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.15, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.16, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.17, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.18, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.19, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.20, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.21, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.22, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.23, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.24, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.25, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.26, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.27, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.28, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.29, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Advances in Virus Research Vol.30, Edited by Max A. Lauffer, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Comprehensive Biochemistry Vol.41: A History of Biochemistry, Personal Recollections VI, Edited by Giorgio Semenza and Rainer Jaenicke, Ch.4 by Lauffer, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Comprehensive Virology 17: Methods Used in the Study of Viruses, Edited by Heinz Fraenkel-Conrat and Robert R. Wagner, Ch.1 by Lauffer, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Electrophoresis: Theory, Methods, and Applications, Edited by Milan Bier, Ch.10 by Lauffer, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology: Polymerization of Tobacco Mosaic Virus Protein and Similar Reactions, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Entropy-Driven Processes in Biology- Reviews and Royalties, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - The Lauffer Farm, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics- Table of Contents & Appendix (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics- Figures (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics- Assorted Material (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.1- "The Electron Microscope" (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.2- "X-ray Diffraction" (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.4- "Light Scattering" (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.5- "Optical Methods" (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.6- "Diffusion" (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.8- "Viscosity" (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics Ch.11- "Electrophysics" (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Methods in Physical Biochemistry & Biophysics- "Sedimentation Velocity" (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Motion in Biological Systems- Figures and Transparencies, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Plant Virology, Edited by M.K. Corbett and H.D. Sisler, Appendix 1 by Lauffer, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Scientific Publications, Bound reprints of previously published articles, 1938-1944 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Subunits in Biological Systems: Part A, Edited by Serge N. Timasheff and Gerald D. Fasman, Ch.4 by Lauffer, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Viral and Rickettsial Infections of Man, Edited by Thomas M. Rivers, Ch.2 by Lauffer, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Viral and Rickettsial Infections of Man Second Edition, Edited by Thomas M. Rivers, Ch.2 by Lauffer, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Assorted Notes from Books (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Books and Booklets Owned by Lauffer, 1943-1990; 3.
    This subseries consists of booklets and books that Lauffer owned. The books were inscribed to him by the authors who were various friends and colleagues. The booklets are on assorted subjects such as nuclear war and various Pitt subjects.
    - Inscribed Books, 1943-1990
      - Bauplane des Lebens: Probleme und Ergebnisse der Biochemie, by Gerhard Schramm, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Comprehensive Biochemistry Vol.37: A History of Biochemistry, Personal Recollections III, Edited by Giorgio Semeza and Rainer Jaenicke, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - A History of the Rockefeller Institute, 1901-1953, Origins and Growth, by George W. Corner, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - The Mathematics of Physics and Chemistry, by Henry Margenau and George Moseley Murphy, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Religion and the State University, Edited by Erich A. Walter, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Student Dictionary of Biology, by Peter Gray, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Ultracentrifugation in Biochemistry, by Howard K. Schachman, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Booklets, 1957-1963
      - "The Effects of Nuclear War on the Pittsburgh Area," A Report by the Pittsburgh Study Group for Nuclear Information, June 1, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Edward Litchfield Inauguration Program, May 11, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - University of Pittsburgh Faculty Handbook & Directory, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - University of Pittsburgh Division of Natural Sciences Bulletin, 1959-1960, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - University of Pittsburgh Graduate Faculty Bulletin, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Extracurricular Involvments, 1952-2011; V.
  This series consists of material related to Lauffer's involvement in various organizations and events. While working at the University of Pittsburgh, he did a variety of work in the Office of the Provost which is represented here. He was also an active member of several scientific organizations, such as The Biophysical Society. In his spare time, Lauffer was heavily involved in the Presbyterian Church and worked in many different subgroups within the organization.
  - Pitt Activities, 1956-1987; 1.
    This subseries consists of material related to Lauffer's work at the University of Pittsburgh outside of his regular duties as a professor and researcher. The bulk of the material relates to his work in the Office of the Provost performing such tasks as departmental reports and serving on task forces.
    - Work with Provost Roger Benjamin, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Consultant to Provost Roger Benjamin, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Chair, Task Force on the Basic Biological Sciences, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
    - Task Force- Feedback, 1983-1985 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Task Force- Minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)